Welcome back everybody.
We are in the Algorithms and Imaginaries
track at the L0
2026 Unsupervised conference.
Thank you for joining us today.
Those of you who are logged in on zoom,
and for those of you who will be watching
in perpetuity over
at the UCF repository
where this conference is stored
today, I'm here to introduce
Professor Leonardo Flores,
who is the chair of the English department
at Appalachian State University
and president of the Latin American
Electronic Literature Network,
which publishes the elite anthologies.
His research areas are electronic
literature, digital writing, and AI,
and he's known for the extensive blog
I e poetry, the Electronic Literature
Collection, volume
three third Gen Electronic Literature,
and the anthology volume one.
He's part of the MLA
Task Force on AI in Teaching and Research,
and co-chaired
its AI in Research Working Group.
He is available to offer talks.
And I've got Leonard here.
He's available
to offer talks and workshops on AI
and its impact on education, policy,
scholarship and creativity.
It was a part of an E!
Poetry workshop at a conference
recently with Leo that was really great,
so I can't recommend it enough.
And he is a cyborg digital writer
with a thriving creative coding practice.
For more information on his current work,
you can visit and out of the florist net.
So please give a round of applause
for Leo.
Welcome!
Thank you so much for giving us keynote.
Thank you. Thank you.
So my talk is
thank you all for being here.
I'm honored by the invitation.
This is my very first keynote
I give for the yellow.
And I'm just so honored to have the chance
to talk to this community
that I hold so dear.
All right.
My talk is is titled Beyond Impossible
Writing Electronic Literature
in the Age of AI.
And over the course of this talk,
you will understand what I mean by this.
And the image is a little bit of a hint
throughout.
You might see some cyborg versions of me.
I call them cyber layouts.
There's a point to it,
you know, cyborg writing and all that.
I don't think I have to explain it
too much to this community.
For those who don't know me.
Who am I? What do I do? Right.
Well, I've been studying and researching
electronic literature for over 25 years.
I served on the MLA Forces
Joint Task Force on and Writing,
which published a number of working papers
offering guidance
to the field on electronic,
on the use of AI in academia policy.
All these things after that team
kind of ended operations, MLA
formed a new task force on AI
and Teaching and Research, which has been
operating for the past year and a half.
And, you know,
we published some statements on AI
and educational technologies and agents
and AI and assessments.
But the most important work
I've been doing was co-chairing the
AI and Research Working Group,
which just published earlier in June,
AI and the Humanities A framework
for Language and Literary Scholarship.
So I really recommend
you take a peek at that guidance.
And there's another working group,
the AI and Pedagogy Working Group, that's
about to publish guidance on that area.
So my goal with this talk
is to bring a little perspective
and a little nuance
to how people are responding to AI,
even in this community.
So part one putting things in perspective.
So I want to highlight some touch points
in computational writing and chatbots.
Right. And this will be familiar
to this community.
Right.
1953 Christopher Stretches Love Letter
Generator
in a way, is one of the foundational works
in our field.
The earliest one we're aware of
actually made with computation, right?
1964 Eliza by Joseph was born.
You know, I wish there was a,
I don't know, booklet study about that
that we could reference.
Anyways, talk about that more later.
1983.
There's a
there's a bunch of other things going
on, interactive fiction
and all these things.
But I'm really focusing on computational
writing as computer generated writing.
You know, Policeman beard is half
constructed by Richter, 1984
a travesty generator for micros
kind of puts Markov chain generators
on the hands of the people.
And why is this moving all right.
There's been a loner prize for chatbots
that lasted
almost 20 years
trying to pass the Turing test.
And, you know, from 2002 to the present,
Philip m Parker has authored over
a million books, several hundred thousand
of which are available, and Amazon.
Burgess
now he's using AI,
but before he was using pre AI
computer generated writing methods.
And, you know, from 2013
to the present, nano gen mode
or National Novel Generation Months
has surpassed 1000 novels generated. And,
you know, some recommended reading.
You can actually read and experience
this history with little anyone.
Bertram and Nick Montfort's
wonderful anthology output, documenting
200 works and 70 years of computation
of computer generated text writing.
And, of course, the hot off the press
inventing Eliza
how the first chatbot
shaped the future of eyes.
We have to read it sideways.
Thank you all by a wonderful team,
including our very own Mark Marina.
One more touch point.
November 30th, 2022 ChatGPT gets launched
and it proved to the general population
that computers were able to pass
the Turing test for writing, right.
All of a sudden
there was a line of demarcation
before that time.
You know, computers generating
text was a quirky thing
that fringe practitioners did,
and all of a sudden anyone could do it.
And this should have been celebrated
as a milestone in computation.
But instead a moral panic ensued.
Essays like the college Essayist dead.
It came out like, what, a week later?
Two weeks later. Yeah. A week later.
Stephen.
Marsha, not nobody is prepared
for how AI will transform academia.
Listen, I get it.
It's it's been it's been pretty bad.
So what does this all look like?
This AI moral panic.
Well, students are going to cheat with AI.
AI is a plagiarism machine.
AI will displace writers and artists.
AI is going to take your job.
A steals your intellectual property.
Kids won't learn to think or create.
An AI is financially unsustainable
and AI is bad for the environment.
And listen, many of these statements
are actually true.
The problem is that AI, like cheating
wasn't invented and plagiarism
wasn't invented.
With AI it existed before, right?
A lot of these
like people losing jobs over
technological developments is nothing new.
Right.
We can think of many, many, many examples.
The very web.
Right?
The very web caused a lot of of job
displacement.
Right?
Like like,
I don't know, travel agents are kind of a
rare thing these days.
And of course, there's really bad
environmental impact.
Now, the problem with the moral panic
is that that source of the moral panic
becomes a scapegoat
for all the other anxieties
that people have,
and that scapegoating is the problem.
So, you know, one piece
that really captured the imagination,
an idea that captured,
that really took hold in the public
imaginary, was this idea
of a bottle of water per email.
Right? Like, here you are.
You sent an email using AI,
and now all of a sudden,
it's like dumping a bottle of water.
That's a very visceral image
that persists to this day.
And this article published in 2024,
September 18th.
Right.
I mean, again, it's not wrong.
It presents information
such as right, this nice infographic,
100 word email generated by an AI chatbot
using
GPT four once requires
a little more than one bottle
519ml of water,
and they do the math once weekly
for a year
requires 27l, about 1.3 water cooler jugs.
Of course, if I have a week
in which I send one email.
My God.
Right. So.
So you can imagine
how this problem compounds
once weekly for a year.
By one out of ten working Americans,
roughly 16 million people requires,
and so on.
It gives the,
you know, equal to the water consumed
by all Rhode Island
households for 1.5 days.
So horrifying. Yes.
Now they take it further.
Right.
Microsoft's data center used 700,000l
of water while training GPT three,
and it takes about 6992l of water
to produce 1 pound of beef,
mostly used to grow, feed, clean
the farm and hydrate cows.
And therefore training.
GPT three has the same water cost
as producing 100 pounds of beef, nearly
double the amount of an average American,
nearly
double the amount in average
American eats in a year.
There's a similar calculation
done with rice.
So the vegetarians have a comparison
point as well. Now,
Ted Underwood
had a really interesting response
that opened my eyes on blue Sky.
I read the article to the end,
where I discovered that one quarter
pound burger equals 3368 emails.
So if I skipped one hamburger,
I can ask a model to write
one email a week for 64 years.
So what's clever
about what Ted Underwood did there
is that he applied the math the other way.
Right.
And so and by the way, 100 pounds of beef.
That's not even a single cow, right?
Just just to give you a sense of scale,
let's look at the data
on on meat production.
Right.
When we think about
I went to our world and data.
This is in 2020 right.
And you can see that land use
change,
farm animal feed processing, transport,
retail and packaging
all generate greenhouse gases.
Right.
That that beef and beef is the worst.
Worst of all the meats.
It's the worst culprit of all.
Followed by Lanman.
Mutton, cheese, beef, dairy herd,
chocolate, coffee,
prawns, farmed palm oil, pig meat,
poultry meat, olive oil, etc.
and we keep going down from there.
Wait a minute.
If people are so concerned with
the environmental impact of AI, I thought,
where's the beef with beef?
Why isn't there a moral panic about beef?
Beeps environmental impact
is 2000 to 2900% worse
than AI's environmental impact?
Of course, many people like beef.
Meat consumption
is part of the status quo.
We've been eating beef for millennia,
and beef isn't disrupting our livelihood.
So? So I get that.
And we need to eat.
So food equals life. Great.
The question is, do we need to eat beef?
Right? By the way, I eat beef.
Just saying.
But we don't need AI.
So AI equals death in this equation.
But don't worry, folks,
the tech industry has a solution.
Here I have screenshots of the main pages
or near the main pages for Beyond Beef
and Impossible
Meats, Beyond Foods and Impossible Foods
because they make things beyond beef,
right?
Like Beyond chicken or Impossible Chicken?
A couple of days ago, I had an impossible
nugget in preparation for this talk.
People, I did this for you.
Anyways,
their websites have
all kinds of hype about I mean, marketing.
I mean information
about their environmental benefits, right?
Beyond Burger and Beyond Steak
become the first base
meat products
that qualify as climate solutions.
See, these people aren't doing it
for the money.
They're doing it to save the planet.
And I love that.
And why eating a Beyond Burger
is better for the planet.
Look at this beautiful Beyond Burger.
I, you know, by sight.
You probably can't tell it apart
from a burger.
And they offer tools like a calculator
where you can choose
right, the the beef
and you can choose different proteins.
How many people are consuming it?
How many times a week.
And so, you know, one person
eating beef once a week
will will,
you know, I mean, using impossible beef
will reduce your water
usage by 1274 gallons
or 14 personal days of water usage.
So there's the campaign, right?
Tech startups to the rescue.
So the the big meat substitute
industry, right?
Both. Impossible.
There's some interesting parallels
with AI and its rise,
both impossible and beyond.
Companies
burst into the market at around 2016.
They are supported by the same venture
capital and stock market that supports AI.
Their products have version numbers.
I think they're in like the three point
something version of both the burgers
and the meats
and the stakes and the chickens.
So so that's great.
There is an ancient history
of meat substitutes.
They didn't invent this.
The industry really started in the 1930s
with the seventh day Adventists.
They were the first to really kind of
kick it up to a
more industrial level. And,
you know, these companies are growing
companies capitalizing on a growing
vegan meat substitute industry.
They present themselves
as technological solutions.
But come on, they're really just
capitalist opportunism.
From the point of view of vegetarians,
they completely missed the point.
And from the point, I mean,
like vegetarian cuisine is a thing, right?
Their entire cultures
that have elaborate vegetarian
cuisines, it's not about finding
like vegetarians aren't craving beef
that they can eat because it's not beef.
It's beyond or impossible beef from
the point of view of meat connoisseurs.
Those of us who like meat,
they completely missed the point.
I mean, they try.
But you know, I ate that impossible nugget
and it was a nugget.
I mean, if you're aiming for the nugget,
you're aiming pretty low, I'll say.
But they do capitalize from those
who can't tell the difference.
And I use the word capitalize on purpose.
I want to keep gesturing towards
capitalism, which is behind all this.
So beyond impossible writing
the title of of of this
or the first half of the title of my talk,
AI generated writing is like impossible
or beyond fake meat products.
It's a big tech solution
and quotation marks an invented problem.
It's fueled by capitalist
or opportunism and hype,
and it completely misses the point.
From the point of view of writing
pedagogy,
reading connoisseurs, literary critic
scholars, electronic literature.
And that's why
I called the first half of my talk
Beyond Impossible Writing
Part two Electronic Literature and AI.
Let's start by defining my terms.
I like to use both
electronic literature and digital writing,
and I define them this way.
Digital writing refers to writing
that embraces the potential digital media
offers to produce generative,
interactive, multimodal, kinetic hypertext
textual works that engage digital culture
to go beyond
the limitations of the page,
whether that is printed or virtual.
Electronic literature is literary
digital writing.
It's an older term in the field,
and it includes practices
that aren't strictly digital writing,
such as sound or video poetry,
and which language is not presented
in written form.
Anyways, that's my definition.
I won't debate it right now.
The situation as a field, we're interested
in going beyond traditional writing,
normative writing, if you will.
But the AI moral panic
has resulted in a reification,
I would say even fetishization
of traditional writing,
and it has resulted in a backlash
against computational writing and bots.
We we heard several examples in Lily von
Bertram's keynote
just a few days ago,
and this is a problem for our field.
At the same time,
AI has tremendous potential
to benefit our field.
This slide,
the next three slides are from a talk
I gave a few years ago in India
about the potential digital writing has,
but I'm also referencing,
you know, a talk I gave on
what's needed to be for electronic
literature to thrive, to exist.
There are three main areas that that need
three conditions that need to be met
for electronic literature.
The first one is access to digital devices
and the internet.
The second is skills, information
and communication technology
skills or ICT skills.
This is a Unesco established term
and they define it as.
Basic skills are like sending an email
with an attachment.
Standard skills are creating
a presentation using presentation software
like a PowerPoint
or whatever, and advanced programing.
And then finally privilege.
You know, Maslow's hierarchy of needs,
you know, puts art and creativity
at the very top of the pyramid.
You have to meet all your other needs
before you're able to create art.
And feel free to create art.
Of course, people create art in
all conditions, but you know what I mean.
Also, access to
a scene, to an audience, to a community,
to a field where this work, this
production at the very least, generates
cultural capital, if not actual capital.
More on that later.
Now, some of you may
be familiar with my work
on third generation electronic literature.
I want to kind of map
this onto the generations.
So the first generation,
if we think of access, well,
computers weren't very available
during the first.
You know,
during the beginnings of computation,
you needed to have access
to a mainframe computer.
Then personal computers came into
the scene in the sort of late 70s 80s.
But if you wanted to do any creation
there, you had to
you had to have advanced ICT skills.
You had to be able to program. Right.
The second generation
from the web, as Hayles conceptualized
from the beginnings of the web,
1995 more or less to the present,
you need access to personal computers,
internet, web hosting.
So there were divides that have been,
you know, narrowed,
but still you needed advanced ICT
skills programing, whether it was HTML,
JavaScript or using advanced
authoring software
like Flash or Director
or some other platforms.
However, platforms like flash, software
like flash lowered that technical barrier
and gave a whole generation
of wonderful writers and artists
the space to create rich multimedia works.
And that's why it was so
and still is so important.
Now, the third generation,
I posited that because what it requires
that access is access to digital devices,
internet, social media networks,
app platforms, mobile devices, touchscreen
devices, smartphones, all those things.
If you have access to that,
then you don't need advanced ICT skills
to create things like a meme
or to use cheap bots done
quick to program and create a bot
and deploy it on Twitter.
May at rest, in peace or in pieces.
And then using, you know,
something like Instagram or TikTok
and generating creating things
videos, images
that you put text on and does things
and share it through these spaces.
So these things are a lot more intuitive.
There are a lot more,
you know, inviting.
And it broadens the the potential creation
in the in the field and in the world.
So some thoughts, right, that I gave
at that talk.
Platforms that require higher ICT skills
perpetuate digital divides and platforms
that require
higher economic investment
perpetuate digital divides.
Right.
So if you have to have a computer
and pay for server space
so you can upload your work, that's
going to slice a whole bunch of people
out of the equation.
But if you have GeoCities
or some other free hosting
that lowers that barrier, right?
Technologies that require lower ICT
skills and lower economic barriers
break these digital divides,
or at least build bridges
across the digital divides.
This is a slide
from presentation that Malda and I gave
yesterday, titled Positioning
Electronic Literature as an Emerging
Creative Industry in the Majority World.
A Comparative analysis
with video games and Digital arts.
Great knack for long titles. Love it.
But notice this adds even further
nuance to the digital divide idea.
There's a
there's three layers of digital divide.
According to to the authors access divide.
Here they're talking about.
In the early half of India's population
still has poor
or no reliable,
affordable internet connectivity.
There's a literacy divide.
Limited digital literacy
among creators constrain the meaningful
use of tools for creative production.
I would say that maps nicely onto the ICT
skills and then outcome divide.
Access
does not translate into empowerment.
Audiences often lack the digital literacy
to interpret and appreciate
ulitsa esthetics,
and I think this is a nice addition
to this idea of privilege and community.
Right?
If you need a you need a community
that gets it and values it.
And heck,
I think the field of electronic literature
worldwide still has that problem.
There are scenes and there spaces
where work is appreciated,
but not in a mainstream way.
How the
divide comes to us, to our community.
It's communicating with computers.
Programing or coding is something that is
very useful to our community and beyond.
When we're able to communicate
with computers, they can do powerful,
powerful things for us.
Programing is an advanced ICT skill.
It takes years to master and continuous
learning to
to to be able to do things with it.
Most of us, I include myself,
don't have the time to dedicate to this,
and this require us to hire
or collaborate
with programmers to get work done.
However, most of us don't have the money
or available programmer
friends to do this.
I wonder how many of the programing
like prowess people
in our community that really advanced
coders in our community
get swamped with invitations
to collaborate for their skills?
So something to to think about the burden
that we might place
on members of our field
who, you know, then have to say no.
Or maybe they say yes and it works.
But anyways, tricky
AI lowers
the technical bar to make programing
coding accessible to us.
Now thinking about
and let's unpack this a little bit.
You know, the lowest level low level
to high level computer languages right.
The lowest level is is binary
machine code.
Right.
You are ones that you're putting in ones
and zeros.
It gives you complete control
over the machine and every aspect of it.
However, it's
very hard to read as a as a human being.
It's very hard to write as a human being.
And so as you move from lowest level
to highest level, notice
that the list goes down.
You have a language, you have CSC
plus plus that gives you
some manual memory and hardware control.
So that's great.
Python JavaScript.
We have human readable code.
I would add Pascal and Basic
and I think Lisp was pretty good.
And other programing languages right.
That are sort of higher level
SQL, HTML you have declarative intents.
But now with AI
we could consider that
to be the highest level prompting.
We use natural language.
It's English or Spanish or Italian.
And you talk in your native language
with the AI system
and it produces the code.
And these AI systems are able to operate
at multiple levels
of computer languages
for us on our behalf.
You know, it's kind of like talking
to a programmer, collaborator
or a person you hired.
You tell them what you want them to do,
they do it.
You see the results.
Maybe they're not exactly
what you thought they were.
So you have a further conversation
where hopefully they are able to
then refine that.
If this is a hired person,
you are accumulating a lot of billable
hours, right?
And again,
I don't want to deny people their salaries
and they're a way to make a living.
But those of us who aren't flush with
money to pay for programmers,
you know,
an AI system can do this for us at a
accessible way, in an accessible way.
Thinking about electronic literature
growth.
Yesterday at a talk here at ELO
Maria,
I made a key point in her presentation
titled code, Poetry and Labor
the Game Excess of work.
Here's the quote.
Code poetry is born out of workers of code
that turn to use their material
for non instrumental, playful and esthetic
means beyond its immediate function,
rather than artists
looking for a new medium of expression.
And that is one wonderful source
of elit growth and development.
As more people develop advanced ICT
skills.
A portion of them will want to express
themselves artistically
and will do so through digital writing,
electronic literature, games
and other digital art forms.
So I think that's wonderful.
But do we want this to be the only growth
vector for electronic literature
and digital writing?
Does it mean that for us to be able
to have more electronic literature
around the world,
and for the field to grow,
it means we have to raise the world's
digital literacy
all the way up
so that enough people are there.
I don't think we have that power.
I don't think we have that ability.
We're talking about re redesigning
entire educational systems,
which to this day are still book and print
based.
As a field,
it behooves us to encourage,
nurture, train, celebrate elit
creation from many other vectors
such as social media
and app platforms, video game
communities, experimental literature,
fanfiction communities, and AI power
empowered creativity.
But what about all the AI slop?
I know, I know, but what about.
Sturgeon theater?
Sturgeon, a science fiction writer,
first formulated.
He gives us the answer here.
Back in 1951,
he formulated this famous adage in which,
you know, he was being interviewed
and people would be like, well.
But so much science fiction is crap
or chloride or slop.
And his response was, well, 90% of
everything is crap.
So, you know, he later, I mean,
it might be true than 90% of science
fiction is crap, but 90% of all writing
and everything is crap.
He later expanded on
this back in 1958, in writing,
and he said, all right.
The revelation
is, 90% of everything is crud.
Corollary one the existence of immense
quantities of trash and science
fiction is admitted.
And it is regrettable,
but it is no more unnatural
than the existence of trash anywhere.
And corollary two
the best science fiction is as good
as the best fiction in any field.
Now, I want you to substitute
science fiction
for like electronic literature,
AI, etc., etc.
and you get the point
I'm trying to make here.
So yeah,
there is increased access
and there is a problem.
Upscale AI has suddenly brought computer
generated writing to the masses.
Loosely defined, a huge
part of the population is now writing
and digital writing.
90% of that is slop, crap, crud,
whatever you want to call it.
And there's so much more of it.
I think when our community was small
in the pre times,
right, I think we had a better percentage
than 90%.
But now we're joining
the rest of the world of writing
and novels
and fiction and poetry and everything,
where we all need to like
cope with being having a 90% crap ratio.
This does not invalidate
the work of our community,
but the AI moral panic and backlash
against AI companies
affects our community.
As I've said before.
The problem with power without knowledge
is that many people can use an AI system
to generate text, images, etc.
but if they're unaware of the history
of computational writing,
the existence of electronic literature,
they're still going to be thinking
of writing as this paper based thing
that people that humans do.
And they have not had the paradigm shift
of how the media transforms
writing and literature.
So yeah, they will initially use
AI to produce traditional writing.
And yes, this is a massive failure
of the imagination,
but they don't even know what to
imagine, right?
I mean, this is where education
is so important.
That kind of writing
I've already compared to the beyond slash
impossible Meat, right? Write it.
It just
misses the point entirely.
I think as a community,
we can help broaden these horizons.
We have been creating resources, archives,
collections, publications, awards.
We have conferences, we have exhibitions,
we have online exhibitions.
We have all kinds of activity
that show how wonderful this can be.
And I think, I don't know, at some point,
hopefully the masses
will discover all these great resources
where we're creating,
but if not, we need to keep, keep pushing
and keep having outreach.
Now let's think about AI as a platform.
So when AI is used to generate
traditional paper based writing, it's
an interesting to me because it shows
how tired traditional writing has become.
I'm not saying it's exhausted, though.
That's a synonym of tired. It's not spent.
It's not over, right?
There's still room to continue developing
this thing we call writing,
even in traditional ways,
even with the, you know,
page, one to page last novel or whatever.
But, you know, like that's that's
where most people are operating,
even with using AI.
I think AI used to generate code
to produce
electronic literature results
in much more interesting results.
It expands the horizon of possibilities,
especially for folks
who don't have the coding skills.
The trick is to use AI to produce, work
in other programing
languages and establish digital platforms.
This way you use AI to create work,
and then you set it aside
and the work lives on in its own platform,
not dependent on AI.
Let's give you a quick example.
I love poetry.
Some of you, if you don't know the history
phase one I wrote 500 daily posts
on Tumblr, reading one poem every day
and writing about it every day.
And that ended up with about 700 pages
of writing when I did the word count.
Phase two, I ported it to WordPress,
I developed metadata,
I invited collaborators,
and we expanded it to over 700 entries.
That went on until like 2017.
From 2017 to 2019, I kind of.
I received a grant to translate it
to Spanish.
I used a WordPress
plugin called WordPress Multilingual
and Pause Development
while we did all this work.
And we did it.
It was translated into Spanish.
It was wonderful.
And then in 2024, the no longer supported
WordPress
multilingual plugin corrupted the database
and crashed the site.
And it was down for two years or so
in January.
Anastasia Salter thank you Anastasia,
I gave a wonderful AI coding
workshop at MLA and I learned
how to taught me how to use Claude code
in an agent way,
and I use Claude code to restore
I Hardy poetry or I love it from a backup
XML file and re-implement
the whole thing on Jekyll,
which is a static site
system.
Now I Heart Poetry is 100% bilingual,
and as a static site
it has minimal dependencies.
It is archive ready.
One more example my creative practice.
I've always been a nerd about programing.
I learned Basic and Pascal in my teens,
HTML in my late 20s.
My scholarly and creative practices
have always been intertwined.
I went through
what I like to call a hacker
period hacker
plus author 2012 through 2022,
in which I adapted other people's code
and made bots
using cheap bots done quick.
Now I'm in a phase.
I call myself a cyborg writer,
and I use AI systems to generate code,
iteratively modifying it by hand
to achieve my creative goals.
This has led to remarkable
creative productivity, and you can see
my creative work
at in my website out of the Flores net.
Let's think about and bring
this to a close
with a thought about AI as infrastructure.
The models these companies are training
aren't just services,
they are infrastructure.
We may not like how,
how or why they're doing it,
but we can still benefit from it.
Let me give you an example.
The Roman Empire now was a Roman Empire
a good thing, historically speaking?
Well, you know,
empires in general are not a great thing.
And this is my cue to bring a nod
to Rupert Garrison's data empire.
Still now hot off the press,
so you should check it out.
Were there some benefits
from the Roman Empire?
Well, you know, Pax Romana
write a little piece with its discontents,
but at least it brought a certain
period of peace and prosperity.
Of course, under the
thumb of the Roman Empire.
Latin became a lingua franca.
It became a commonly spoken language
throughout the region,
and it became the foundation
for romance languages.
Infrastructure.
They created aqueducts.
They created extensive road systems.
And really,
do we need to weigh in and have a cost
benefit analysis of the Roman Empire
at this point?
No, it happened right.
I think we're in a similar situation.
I think people feel this pressure
to do a cost benefit analysis of AI,
and I think it's rather unfair.
Here's a map from Wikipedia of
of of the roads
that the Roman Empire built.
Pretty extensive.
This was important infrastructure
for the time.
I don't think that part of the world
had seen infrastructure like this.
But AI infrastructure
can be used against the
the people who create it, right?
Like the barbarians used
those very same roads
to usher the fall of the Roman Empire.
I think we can use AI infrastructure
to work against the interests of big
AI or,
you know, however we define the problem,
I think we can use it
to develop our own projects,
creative and critical.
And I would like for you to consider open
local models
versus Frontier Cloud
proprietary corporate models.
Let's elaborate on this.
So local AI you can use your computer
to use AI systems.
You can download them onto your computer,
install them.
They run for free.
You know, offline their private.
They don't rely on data centers.
And sure, they may
not be as versatile
and powerful as the frontier models,
but that need for compression
leads to specialized models.
Here's a little graph of a number of
of models, for example.
You know,
and this kind of like Google Gamma four
is supposed to be highly scalable and
and give you
native low latency
audio vision and agent efficiency.
So that's an important breakthrough when
three is specialized for code generation.
And it is very multilingual.
That's what I used to create my most
recent work of electronic literature.
Deep seek Microsoft Mistral, like
most of the major companies
are, are producing
and publishing open models.
And this is a really important
infrastructural
contribution.
The cons of local AI.
Well, they're not as powerful
as as a big frontier models.
Yeah, admittedly they're a genetic
and multimodal
capabilities are still developing.
Some say they're
they're about six months behind.
They can be slower depending on your
the model you're using
and your computer hardware.
So next time you buy a computer you might
want to splurge a little on that.
There's a good
principle called the good stewardship
principle that I learned from
an AI influencer called shea ammonia.
And you know what I mean?
Like, I knew the concept.
She really applied it very effectively
to AI and local AI.
In a nutshell, it's the idea of
using the right tool for the job
and using the tool that will cause
the sort of least environmental impact.
For example,
I'm shifting to Quinn and Gamma,
local open models for creative coding.
Again, my creative coding isn't on the
scale of some people's creative coding.
I use cloud code when I need a genetic
AI capabilities
and more advanced coding problems.
Or occasionally
I might be using my local model
and I hit a wall in terms of development,
and Claude can help me
get over that wall, address
that issue better.
But again, it's spot
treating instead of using it all the time.
I use Gemini for some image generation
and a little bit of research support
in a metaphor of use before even earlier
today.
Listen, I don't need a tank to drive
to the grocery store.
My fuel efficient car is better
for the job, right?
The tank is going to just cause
all kinds of trouble along the way.
So? So, yeah.
Now what?
Well, we.
And by we, I mean we all.
You two need to decide if you use
AI to benefit our work or not.
For some, it's not worth it.
Totally respect it.
For others, it is.
We hopefully respect each other's
decisions.
Unfortunately, that is not the case
with a lot of the AI moral panic.
And so there's like almost like an
AI cancel culture
going out there and backlash against AI,
not against the big.
Well, yes, against the big companies,
but also against creators,
also against, for example,
the editors of the ELC five.
ET cetera.
I think we need to respect
each other's decisions,
and I think we need to think twice
before casting stones.
Yes, it's a biblical Jesus reference
because there is no ethical consumption
in their capitalism.
If someone goes on Facebook,
which uses exactly the same infrastructure
and has well-documented social ills,
social and environmental, and,
you know, we can add to
the list is to attack me
for using AI.
Listen, I'm
sorry if I don't take you to seriously,
but you are critiquing the infrastructure
of the very same building.
We're both standing in.
I want to remind this community in 2011
published an important essay
that resonated in our community
why I have Stopped Creating it.
And he raised
many of the very same concerns
that we have right now about AI.
Except back then
he was raising these concerns about you.
No data centers that people really worry
about, data centers beyond the
and some other folks, a handful of folks
that people really complain
about data centers before
AI a little bit,
not at the scale
we're we're we're doing it now.
He stepped away from Illit
for several years and then came back
and is doing really important and ethical
and and you know,
he found a way
to resolve the ethical quandaries
that this damned capitalist system world
we live in
makes us do, makes us
do, have make impossible choices.
But I'm still angry
and worried about AI and its impacts.
Well, yeah, I am too.
But how about we direct
our anger against AI's adverse
effects towards the big
AI companies that are causing them?
There's so much work to be done
to mitigate, regulate
and hold them accountable.
But also if AIC enemy no then enemy
use their tools against them.
That amount is an important situation,
a strategy
in which you use the tools
of of of the system against it for art.
Art is a form of resistance.
Remember none of these platforms,
most of these platforms
were not created for us to make art in it.
But we are human beings
and we make art wherever we can.
Poetic mischief AI interrogation.
Thank you.
Lilian. Yvonne, for those terms.
They're great.
And more.
And read, learn, strategize, vote,
do other things because AI is already here
and we need to reckon with it
and hopefully benefit from
it, warts and all.
Thank you.
And I will
publish my slideshow in my website
net tomorrow.
Thank you.
Plastic provocation
and some great responses
to some of the concerns
raised by our colleagues who,
especially
if you're in an English department,
may not be feeling the most receptive
to electronic literature
and generative text face to face.
Yeah, folks, I had to.
I had to completely cut off the chat
from my field of vision
because it was distracting me.
So I'm going to go back,
but I'm here for questions.
So yeah,
please jump in.
Raise your hand
or throw a question to chat.
I haven't seen any actual questions.
The shot.
So the chat is very entertaining.
Looking forward to that.
Yeah I have a question.
It's kind of a loaded question.
And I think you touched on this
a little bit.
Do you see any scenario
where we become obsolete?
Our he let people us
because of a problem of people
outside our closed society
making it right and left all the time,
which they've been doing,
as you point out for a while
now, and we just get left behind.
We are the forerunners,
but the forerunners don't win the race.
Do you foresee that possibility?
Yeah. And you know what?
I'm okay with that possibility because
it means that Ellett is here to stay.
I would not want us to be
a forgotten little chapter
in some corner of a book
that said, you know, for a few years,
a couple of oddballs made some illit.
They called it illit.
It was a French practice. And.
Yeah.
No, that was that was that.
You know, I'd rather eel it becomes
part of literature, part of art,
part of expression
in the world.
Thank you.
Yeah, yeah.
Other.
Or more comment than a question.
Dina asked.
Places
where there's little internet or access
that spread.
What was that again about using
AI tools in places where there is
little internet or kind of access.
So accessibility of AI tools,
you can install them on a local machine
and run it.
So yeah,
you don't need the internet for that.
You don't need cloud services for that.
And these tools have come a long way
from the early days of the open model.
So yeah, take a take offline illit
AI into communities and help people code.
Yeah.
And do you have a guidebook for that?
You know,
I have I have my,
my cyborg digital writing
primer has some steps towards that.
It's not a super elaborate one,
but it's actually not hard to do.
So I updated it recently.
You can check it out.
It's on my website.
I will see if I can find it and share it
with you real quick in the chat.
And then you can you can learn to do it.
It is not hard to do.
I was wondering if you could say
a little bit about the reaction
you've gotten from, like,
the MLA community
to your perspective on this,
if you've put.
Well, listen, I haven't exactly
I mean, listen,
I haven't super shared this
because I know that electronic literature
is not a mainstream practice.
What I do when I do my work with the MLA
is and the task forces
and the working groups I'm a part of
is I bring perspective into this.
I bring the perspective that our field
and the insights that that I've developed
and our field has developed.
Because I'm not just me, I'm I'm me.
And and and the discourse of this field
to bear on some of
this so that we don't end up
reaffirming,
you know, a romantic idea of writing
as, as,
you know, this person selecting one word
and then another
entirely out of their brain and
putting them in sequences and all that.
So and of course,
I also bring my experience as a,
as a, as a leader, as a department chair,
as an English professor,
as someone who write, who studies
all this. And.
Yeah, so, so basically I work with teams
with really smart people
who know more about some of these things,
and we join the conversation
and we work things through
and we make our recommendations.
I think that's great. I think you should.
I think it'd be great if you did
this more outside of the the community.
I was just I just did
an interview with folks in Bruno Latour
lab who are now
researching everyday use of AI,
and they their commentary was that
they talked to a lot of people
who discovered
that they were and discovered,
as they were talking about it,
that they used
AI a lot in their everyday life,
but that they felt like they couldn't
admit it
because there's so much shame
attached to the use of this now.
And I think trying to distinguish
between legitimate uses,
and also for the necessity of artists
to engage with these technologies, to
not just leave it to to corporate goals
and to for, for for corporations
to entirely bend the tools
using the tools that they make
as well as using smaller models.
So important.
So thanks I think this is great.
Thank you Scott.
That means a lot. I'll add, you know,
one of the recent operas, right?
When Google announced
that they were now going to integrate
AI further
into their search engines. Right.
And that sort of search engine is over.
And the other one and it's like, no,
we can't trust the AI.
I'm switching to duck. Duck. Great.
Do the things that make you feel good
about it.
However, you know Safiya moya Noble's
algorithms of oppression.
It's not like we had this great system
for search that had no politics or biases.
And now AI is inserting all these biases.
No, no.
Those were always already there. Right?
So if you're going to use a Google service
for searching and finding information,
you know, pick the model
the best suits you.
I don't know if if any of you
have been making the adjustment,
but I'm now asking questions on the Google
search bar
rather than keywords,
and that is a little paradigm shift
in how we search and find information.
So again,
let's let's think through these things.
Let's get past our gut response
and really kind of explore these things.
Other questions or comments.
Oh there's AI that runs on mobile
phones too.
They're pretty modest little models.
But let's face it, mobile phones
aren't great for coding anyways.
So yeah, you could have a little AI system
on your phone.
I personally don't find
a tremendous amount of utility to it.
I'd rather use the one that's
more connected to the cloud services
because I can, you know,
like if I'm traveling somewhere
and I see something and it's not labeled,
I just got back from a lovely trip
with a family to England and Scotland.
I could take a picture of something
and ask the AI system, what is this?
What am I looking at?
And it'll search
and I'll try to give you an answer,
and I'll take that answer
with a grain of salt.
But it's it's better than just
not not knowing.
Oh, I see a good question.
Teagan wants to respond to the question
why is it good?
Or Alison's question why is he look good?
Listen, here's why Elit is good.
That's a actually excellent question.
Why do we even do this?
Listen, part of my response
I've.
I've been long enough in this field,
working in English departments,
working with people
who just don't get what it is
that I do with elit and all that,
both as scholar, as a scholar
and as a creator
that I frequently have
to find my find myself
justifying electronic literature.
Here's my justification.
I think it gives us
a glimpse into the future
of digital writing, of writing and digital
media, of human artistic expression
in digital media.
I think in the future,
when these things, folks,
let's remember,
this is still early days, right?
This is like digital literacy program
encoding all these things.
They're not part of most,
most school curricula.
It's the privileged, highly private,
special schools
that get that kind of investment.
But really,
until code
literacy and coding
just becomes as normal as writing on paper
or on a, on a computer,
virtual paper word processor,
you know, it's it's not going to become
quite normalized, right?
So with electronic literature,
both in its past
and in its present
and in its many, many iterations.
Right.
Like what might writing
look like in a virtual space?
What might writing look like
in a sort of X or AR kind of space?
when it's written through with variables
and algorithms?
What does writing look like
when it's multimodal?
when it's interactive?
Right?
What does writing look like
when it combines many or all of those
things are digital data or installations
or all these things?
Our community, this thing we call Elit,
is a freaking lab, an experimental lab
for human expression in
with digital media in its capabilities.
And I think, I think that's the future.
I will say that out, you know,
come back to me and many more years
if there's an afterlife
or a digital afterlife or whatever.
Go find me and tell me.
I don't believe in any
of those things, but, you know, whatever.
If we bump into each other
in the long picture,
so be it, you know?
We'll see.
We'll see if I was right
or if I was wrong.
But in the meantime, we do
the work as best we know.
And we, you know, we try to nurture
the best practices.
Well, I can't imagine
a better note to end on than that.
Thank you so much.
That was fantastic.
And there are only four events
left in the conference, folks.
So please play another round of applause
and check out the two concurrent sessions.
We have
individual papers starting up
here, and our panel on the first web novel
as 30,
starting up on just a few minutes
over on the Hypertext
and Fictions track,
which is about to launch.
So please consider
switching over or hanging around here
for more yellow.
And after that, we do have the town hall.
With the 2027 conference announcement
and our award ceremony
to celebrate members of the community
and wrap up this four day adventure.
So I hope you'll consider sticking around
this afternoon and joining us.
Thank you all.